<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Holy-Rood House, January 30. 1681/2. before Her Highness the Lady Anne. Tho. Cartwright ...</title>
            <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1634-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35074</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C704A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170908</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13682496</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13682496</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101317</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35074)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101317)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 841:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Holy-Rood House, January 30. 1681/2. before Her Highness the Lady Anne. Tho. Cartwright ...</title>
                  <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1634-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by David Lindsay ;</publisher>
                  <publisher>and sold by Walter Davis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <pubPlace>and reprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing C704 is distinguished from C704A by the lack of the word "by" in statement of responsibility on t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Acts VII, 60 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101317:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at HOLY-ROOD-HOUSE, <hi>January</hi> 30. 1681/2. Before Her Highneſs the Lady ANNE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THO. CARTWRIGHT,</hi> D.D. Dean of <hi>Ripon,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His <hi>Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>David Lindſay,</hi> and reprinted at <hi>London,</hi> and ſold by <hi>Walter Davis,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101317:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101317:2"/>
            <head>TO HER HIGHNESS THE LADY ANNE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving had the Honour to be ſerviceable to your Devotions, by Preaching in your Royal Chappel, on the Anniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Remembrance of your Royal <hi>Grand-father</hi> of bleſſed Memory; and received your gracious Approbation of my Sermon then, and your Commands ſince to publiſh it, for the benefit of them who could not croud in to hear it: It would be a Proteſtation againſt that Obedience which I preſs'd upon others as their Duty, if I ſhould not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily give up it, and my ſelf, in all Humility, to your Service.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101317:3"/>
            <p>As many as ſhall think fit to peruſe it, will here find recommended two of the greateſt Examples of Zeal and Piety; of Patience and Constancy; the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Martyr St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> and the <hi>firſt Chriſtian Prince</hi> who ever ſealed his Religion with his Blood; concerning whom, I hope I have ſaid enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the Reader, that Death and the Grave have no power over his immortal Name; that the ſharpeſt Sword of his most malicious Enemies cannot wound it, nor the venom of Adders poyſon it. His <hi>Body</hi> lyes buried in a <hi>peaceable obſcurity,</hi> but His <hi>Fame</hi> is Immortal like his Soul, and his righteouſneſs ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance; and that <hi>his Enemies</hi> are now as <hi>ridiculous and vile,</hi> as they would have rendred the <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi> God hath ſhewed them to the World, to be the <hi>very Perſons they were,</hi> and the <hi>ſubtile Artifices</hi> of their wicked Contrivances, upon which they <hi>wrote his Name,</hi> to be the Suggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>their Father the Devil;</hi> he hath reſcued <hi>his,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi>'s Glory, out of their Hands; nor ſhall they be able again to inveſt <hi>Impiety</hi> and <hi>Injuſtice</hi> with the Titles of his <hi>Providence and Spirit.</hi> I hope, we ſhall never live to ſee the <hi>Defender of the Faith</hi> any more deſtroyed for <hi>Conſcience-ſake,</hi> as we did that <hi>Glorious Martyr,</hi> of whom the World was not worthy. His <hi>Blood</hi> does ſtill run in your <hi>Royal Veines;</hi> and you have prov'd your ſelf to have ſuch an eminent ſhare of <hi>his Piety</hi> hitherto, that we have no reaſon to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:101317:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> but you will <hi>continue</hi> a <hi>Glorious Pattern</hi> of the ſame to your Lives end, and remain conſtant in that <hi>truly Catholick Religion,</hi> for which <hi>he dyed;</hi> for your <hi>adherence</hi> to which, <hi>your Fame</hi> is already ſo deſervedly <hi>Great</hi> in theſe Kingdoms; in which Faith, that you may ſtedfastly continue, until your <hi>Graces</hi> be Crown'd with <hi>Eternal Glory,</hi> you have the dayly Prayers of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt obedient and dutiful Servant, <hi>Tho. Cartwright.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:101317:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101317:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at <hi>HOLY-ROOD-HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE</hi> 30. <hi>January</hi> 1681/2.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>7 Acts. Verſe 60.</bibl>
                  <p>And he kneeled down, and cryed with a loud voyce, Lord, lay not this ſin to their charge, and when he had ſaid this, he fell aſleep.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F when <hi>Anthony</hi> brought <hi>Caeſars bloody Robe</hi> into the Market-place, the People were obſerved by the <hi>Orator</hi> to be in a tumult, and ſo paſſionately affected, <hi>ut non occiſus eſſe Caeſar, ſed tune maxime occidi videre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> that they looked not upon his murder, as a thing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101317:5"/> already done and paſs'd, but as if he were now bleeding under the Parricid's hands; then ſure, if we are not that <hi>Durum genus</hi> which <hi>Ovid</hi> fancies, nor thoſe <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren which were raiſs'd up to</hi> Abraham <hi>of Stones;</hi> it will not be poſſible for <hi>me</hi> to mention without horror, nor yet for <hi>you</hi> to remember without aſtoniſhment, that exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable thing which was as on this day done among us. That, which we are now met to commemorate, is the greateſt <hi>victime</hi> which was ever ſacrificed to divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, ſince Chriſt himſelf, in ſo ignoble a way: for the <hi>moſt Glorious Sun</hi> that ever ſhon in the Firmament of the Brittiſh Throne, was this day <hi>turn'd to blood;</hi> the mortality of our moſt Gracious, Soveraign Lord, CHARLES the Firſt, Crown'd with Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; the relation whereof (if I could ſuppoſe it were not ſtill freſh in your memories) though but <hi>weakly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd,</hi> would certainly be a very <hi>forcible argument,</hi> to engage you to that humiliation, which is juſtly to be expected from you; But, alas, I may eaſily be confident, that you have <hi>all</hi> ſadly felt the incomparable <hi>ſmart</hi> of that <hi>fatal blow,</hi> it being the heavieſt ſtroak that ever did light upon a diſtracted Kingdom, and of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious conſequences, that the Children that are yet unborn, may have abundant reaſon to curſe thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrallel'd villanies that gave it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Noble Army of Martyrs</hi> is the ſupreme of all <hi>Orders</hi> in the Church, both Militant and Triumphant; and he who was lately <hi>Ours</hi> is now a <hi>Prince of them,</hi> whoſe <hi>paſſion</hi> we are now met on this <hi>fatal day</hi> to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate, as that which deſerves: to have the greateſt price ſet upon it, next to that of our Saviour, for as no vollyes of perſecutions (though diſcharg'd ſo thick as God knows they were againſt him) could drive him from the <hi>maintenance</hi> of his <hi>Subjects Rights</hi> and <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> ſo was he a <hi>Defender of the true Catholick and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolick
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101317:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> Faith</hi> indeed, for he went with it to the <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold</hi> and took <hi>his death</hi> upon it, and I perſwade my ſelf; I am now ſpeaking to thoſe, ſome of whoſe <hi>pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Souls</hi> have not yet left off their <hi>Cloſe mourning</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>He <hi>humbled himſelf to death,</hi> even to the death upon the Block, <hi>for the joy that was ſet before him he endured</hi> the bloody ſtroak of the Axe and <hi>deſpiſed the ſhame,</hi> in the <hi>hope</hi> and comfort of a <hi>bleſſed reſurrection</hi> he layd down his head and <hi>dyed in the Lord</hi> and <hi>for him,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">14 Rev. 13. 2 Heb. 10.</note> the Royal Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr followed the <hi>Captain of our Salvation,</hi> that he might be <hi>made perfect through ſufferings;</hi> and as Chriſt, though he could, with leſs than a word, have diſpatched his <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders</hi> quick into Hell, yet never ſo much as <hi>open'd his mouth,</hi> ſave only <hi>to pray that they might be forgiven,</hi> and that the extreme act of their malice might be the only means of their Salvation: ſo, though the King had a Spirit not to be <hi>outbrav'd</hi> with the Terror of an Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet did not <hi>their cruelty,</hi> exceed the meaſures of <hi>his charity,</hi> who <hi>call'd for no fire from Heaven,</hi> but that of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine love,</hi> to burn up his unnatural Subjects hatred and animoſities to each other; this great and <hi>Chriſtian Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote</hi> he had againſt <hi>their malice,</hi> and what a <hi>Royal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge</hi> his charity gave him upon and victory over his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, let ſome of his laſt words convince you.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>I bleſs God, I pray not ſo much that this bitter cup of a violent death may paſs from me, as that, that of his wrath may paſs from all thoſe, whoſe hands by deſerting me are ſprinkled, or by acting and conſenting to my death are imbrued in my blood.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt therefore I am to diſcourſe, of theſe <hi>laſt words</hi> of the <hi>first Chriſtian Martyr St.</hi> Stephen, who was one of the 70 Diſciples, choſen by Chriſt to be a <hi>Coadjutor</hi> to his Apoſtles, in the work of the Miniſtry, a Perſon every way qualified with Zeal and Piety for the ſervice
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101317:6"/> of the Church, whoſe <hi>Crown</hi> of Glory is platted in his <hi>name;</hi> I am ſure, I ſhall not be to ſeek for a <hi>Parallel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His caſe was this, his enraged Enemies not only <hi>ſought</hi> his blood, but with an impatient and miſguided Zeal they ſhed it, and yet he not only pardon'd them himſelf, but with <hi>bended knees and ane loud voyce</hi> (arguing <hi>the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Spirit</hi>) he prays to God to pardon them; which ſpeaks him <hi>full of Faith and the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour did the ſame before him, our Soveraign of bleſſed Memory, ſince him. <hi>And he kneel'd down, and cryed with a loud voyce, Lord, lay not this ſin to their charge, and when he had ſaid this, he fell aſleep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have a <hi>large Field,</hi> to lead you over, and that an <hi>Aceldama</hi> a <hi>Field of blood,</hi> a <hi>Tragical Theme</hi> to diſcourſe of; in which I ſhall make no longer ſtay, then only to ſhew you theſe following particulars, reducible to 3 ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral heads, the <hi>Preface,</hi> the <hi>Prayer</hi> and the <hi>Date</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>1.</label> In the <hi>Preface</hi> there are 3 things obſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Petitioner,</hi> to whom the Pronoun <hi>He</hi> refers us, St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> whoſe <hi>honour,</hi> I have not now leiſure to <hi>blazon,</hi> nor yet to make that <hi>just report,</hi> which another time might challenge me to do of him, who <hi>firſt paſs'd through the red Sea of Martyrdome,</hi> and ſuffered for our Saviour 3 years after him; the moſt <hi>glorious performance,</hi> of which a creature is capable, and the moſt <hi>advantagious</hi> too: For if he who gives a <hi>Cup of cold Water ſhall not loſe his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> no doubt but he ſhall find it who gives a <hi>draught of warm blood,</hi> and that his <hi>heart-blood</hi> too; and therefore the Primitive Martyrs counted it as their higheſt prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Humility of his poſture;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vſ. 59.</note> when he pray'd for <hi>himſelf he ſtood,</hi> but as if his <hi>Enemies Souls</hi> were <hi>dearer</hi> to him than his own, our humble ſupplicant falls <hi>on his knees</hi> for them; <hi>and he kneeld down.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The fervency of his Spirit</hi> argued from his <hi>hearty</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101317:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>zealous outcry.</hi> His voyce was not ſo <hi>low</hi> before for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but that 'tis now as <hi>high</hi> for them; he had need <hi>cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud</hi> indeed who intercedes for the Pardon of ſuch a <hi>crying ſin</hi> as theirs: for he who <hi>bottles up his Servants tears,</hi> will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly make an account of their <hi>blood,</hi> the Tongue whereof is always hoarſe. <hi>Abels cryes ſtill,</hi> (ſo I fear does the Kings) nor will St. <hi>Stephens</hi> eaſily be ſilenced at his greateſt inſtance: And therefore when he kneel'd and pray'd for his murderers, it was, ſaid in the Text, with a <hi>loud voyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>2.</label> In the Prayer we muſt alſo obſerve 3 things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Subjectum cui,</hi> the party to whom it is directed, to <hi>him</hi> who had ſo lately ſuffered for and before him, to <hi>his</hi> and <hi>our Lord,</hi> the <hi>Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Subjectum de quo;</hi> the perſons for whom he inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes, when he could ſcarce gain time to think of his <hi>friends,</hi> he is <hi>praying for his Enemies. Lyramus</hi> ſaith, that in ſome copies 'tis added, <hi>for they know not what they do;</hi> but for the moſt part they were mov'd (like the Kings Enemies) more by <hi>paſſion</hi> than <hi>ignorance,</hi> and even that ignorance of many was <hi>pravae diſpoſitionis,</hi> cauſed by a <hi>preceding malice:</hi> For they were <hi>cutt to the heart,</hi> they <hi>gnaſh'd on him with their teeth,</hi> and they <hi>stop'd their ears</hi> (and ſo they alſo did to the gracious Meſſages of the <hi>martyr'd King</hi>) and <hi>ran upon him with one accord and ſton'd him;</hi> and yet he knew not how to be angry with them, for taking away his <hi>Temporal,</hi> becauſe they haſtned his <hi>Eternal happineſs.</hi> Eternal Life was the <hi>Crown</hi> of ſuch a ſuffering, but <hi>Eternal death</hi> the <hi>wages</hi> of ſuch a <hi>ſin;</hi> which that it might not be the <hi>portion of their cup to drink</hi> he prayes; <note place="margin">11 Pſal. 6.</note> nor was his prayer loſt: For <hi>Saul</hi> who was a principal perſon in it, had not <hi>this ſin layd to his charge</hi> as himſelf witneſſeth, <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 13.</note> but was gaind to the Church by St. <hi>Stephen</hi>'s prayer, ſays St. <hi>Augustin, Si Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus non ſic oraſſet, Eccleſia Paulum non haberet;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug. Serm. 1. de S. Steph.</note> So ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, no doubt, were to their <hi>Loyalty</hi> by thoſe of our <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr'd Soveraign.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101317:7"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Subjectum circa quod,</hi> the ſubject matter of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, or that which he craves in their behalf is Pardon. <hi>Lay not this ſin to their charge.</hi> He does not pray to God, not to <hi>repute it a ſin,</hi> it were impoſſible for the <hi>juſt Judge</hi> to juſtifie ſuch an <hi>unjuſt action,</hi> but that he <hi>would not impute it to them.</hi> God is not like men, apt to <hi>forget ſins,</hi> as ſoon as they are committed, <hi>he beholdeth miſchief and wrong,</hi> and he <hi>writes bitter things againſt them,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">10 Pſal. 14. 13 Job. 20.</note> nor will he quickly <hi>blot them out of the Book of his remembrance.</hi> And though he do not always <hi>let looſe his Thunder</hi> to ſtrike thoſe <hi>men of blood,</hi> to whom his ſevereſt Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is due; yet we know not upon what <hi>Strapado</hi> their ſouls are ſometimes toſt, in what a continual Allarum that <hi>fury</hi> keeps their Conſciences, and what an Hell they have within them; nor will God, who now <hi>walks upon the face of the waters, that his footſteps are not ſeen,</hi> ſuffer this his forbearance to paſs for a payment, for when he <hi>makes inquiſition for blood,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">9 Pſal. 12.</note> he will remember it. St. <hi>Stephen</hi> knew, that whilſt his Enemies continued in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without repentance, it would be in vain to dream of any device to tye the hand of an Almighty Vengeance, from ſeizing on them. <hi>Christ</hi> hath not born the ſins of the impenitent; they themſelves muſt: he therefore prays for their faith and repentance, that ſo they may be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Gods favour, who were under his wrath, that the <hi>hand-writing</hi> which was iſſued out againſt them might <hi>be canceld,</hi> and that God in Chriſt would in mercy recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile them to himſelf; this <hi>in Heaven</hi> is call'd a <hi>not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſin,</hi> and in the <hi>Souls of ſinful men,</hi> 'tis a reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their rebellious natures to truth and goodneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>3.</label> Laſtly we are to obſerve the <hi>Date and timing of his Petition;</hi> 'twas in the extremity of his Paſſion, for <hi>when he had ſaid this, he fell aſleep, Obdormivit in Domino—ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem exuit,</hi> he willingly puts off the Fleſh, as a weary man does his Cloaths, and compoſes himſelf to reſt. The
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101317:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>hard Stones</hi> are a <hi>ſoft Pillow</hi> to his innocent Head. Death is but the <hi>bodies Bed-Chamber</hi> in which it ſleeps, till the Soul return to awaken it at the Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Theſe and more incidental Circumſtances are full of ſuch variety with which I might pardonably entertain you at any time but this; to wear out any part whereof, in ſuch unneceſſary <hi>diverſions,</hi> as might call me off from this <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly ſolemnity,</hi> would, I am ſure, be too groſs an abuſe of <hi>your patience,</hi> and of this <hi>ſolemn day of Humiliation;</hi> in which if I ſhall chance to give you <hi>Epimetronti,</hi> ſomething more than the meaſure of an <hi>ordinary Sermon</hi> upon ſuch an <hi>Extraordinary Theme and Time:</hi> at leaſt, when your <hi>patience</hi> gives me over, <hi>endure</hi> the reſt as an <hi>eaſie Penance</hi> for the <hi>heavy Sin</hi> of the day.</p>
            <p>And I hope you will not think that I ſhake hands with my Text, whilſt I take this <hi>juſt occaſion</hi> of ſhowing you, how well it does accord with <hi>the Time,</hi> comparing the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal stain</hi> of this day, with the <hi>Sin</hi> of that, and the <hi>guilt of the Regicides,</hi> with that of the <hi>Jews;</hi> by which we may be the better convinced, that, as the <hi>King himſelf</hi> of his <hi>Princely Pity</hi> to us did, ſo had we need to cry aloud for our Pardon, humbling our ſelves, and renouncing that abhorred murder, of God's <hi>Anointed Servant,</hi> and our <hi>lawful Soveraign;</hi> leaſt when he come to make <hi>inquiſition for Blood,</hi> his innocent Royal blood be ſtill juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us and our Poſterities.</p>
            <p>Now though the <hi>Charitable Martyr</hi> hid his Enemies ſin, in ſuch a <hi>terminus diminuens,</hi> as the cloſe Phraſe of <hi>this ſin;</hi> yet, the <hi>faithful Miniſter</hi> may not: 'tis for him, to <hi>ſearch</hi> it, that he may ſee, whether it be not like that of <hi>Cain,</hi> greater than could be forgiven.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſin</hi> therefore, though but expreſs'd in two words, muſt be explain'd in many more, 'tis a <hi>comprehenſive Villany,</hi> its name is <hi>Legion;</hi> never any ſin had ſo great a train of Hell as this; it is like a Mathematick Line diviſible, <hi>in ſemper diviſibilia;</hi> I ſhall but reckon up its Aggravations,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101317:8"/> as the <hi>unjust Steward</hi> did <hi>his Maſters debts,</hi> of a <hi>thouſand, ſet down but fifty:</hi> and yet I expect to tire my ſelf and you too before I leave it.</p>
            <p>Gentle Language does but <hi>water Sin,</hi> and make it grow again; and he who <hi>treats it civilly,</hi> is guilty of its <hi>increaſe:</hi> which I would be loath to be of <hi>Rebellion;</hi> and yet ſhould we ſtrain courteſie with this, the moſt <hi>plauſible term</hi> we could give it, would be <hi>Murder;</hi> a ſin which like an armed Gyant, will firſt or laſt ſet upon its Authors, and rend them with inward torments. And 'tis therefore above all other ſins, ſo <hi>hedg'd about with Thornes,</hi> even in <hi>this life,</hi> 'tis ten to one but <hi>Vengeance</hi> meets it. 'Tis <hi>ſcelus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fandum,</hi> a wickedneſs too great for any expreſſion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Act it</hi> ſelf is <hi>abominable,</hi> but the <hi>Object</hi> makes it <hi>execrable;</hi> a ſin out of meaſure ſinful; ſuch a ſtupendious Villany it was, as our poſterity will hardly find Faith enough to believe. 'Tis the Murder, not of a <hi>private man,</hi> but of a King, the beſt of men. And if <hi>Alexander</hi>'s killing of <hi>Caliſthenes,</hi> was in <hi>Seneca</hi>'s Judgment <hi>crimen aeternum,</hi> what ſhall ſo damnable a Paracide, this Regicide, be in ours? If ever any Corps deſerved to ſwim in Teares, 'twas <hi>his.</hi> And if ever any Villany did match that of the Jews, in the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying of Our <hi>Saviour,</hi> 'twas theirs, in the Beheading of <hi>Our most gracious Sovereign:</hi> For he was not ſuch a <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah</hi> to us, as to change a Kingdom of Free-men, into an <hi>Houſe of Bondage.</hi> He neither <hi>enſlaved:</hi> us in our <hi>Perſons, Labours, Poſſeſſions</hi> nor <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings;</hi> (and 'tis a great Truth, which may be ſaid without danger of Flattery, that <hi>His Son</hi> walkes after him) nay ſo much greater was His care <hi>for us</hi> than <hi>himſelf,</hi> that how much ſoever our <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching fingers</hi> itch'd to be tampring with <hi>his Prerogative;</hi> (as they ſtill do with <hi>His Son's</hi>) he took care, we ſhould be abridged <hi>no liberty of the Subject,</hi> unleſs it were <hi>a Licence of deſtroying our ſelves:</hi> (of which we <hi>in this Age</hi> ſeem as fond, as in <hi>the last,</hi>) and ſo far was He from invading our Rights, that none was ever ſo forward <hi>to part with his own,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101317:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> (in which, I pray God, His Son, <hi>Our gracious Soveraign</hi> walk not too much after him) diminiſhing it in <hi>ſo many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,</hi> as left him open at laſt to the loſing of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>Witneſs the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> paſſed by him, in <hi>June,</hi> 1628. An <hi>Act of ſuch Royal grace,</hi> as might eaſily have put us into an extaſy of admiration: In ſo much as that when he <hi>paſſed that Bill,</hi> he almoſt dealt with his People, as <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> did with his <hi>Praetorian prefect,</hi> put his Sword into their hands, and bid them uſe it <hi>for him,</hi> if he ruled well, if not, <hi>against him;</hi> he acted rather like a <hi>Steward</hi> for his people, than a <hi>Lord over them;</hi> and ſo would <hi>his Son</hi> do too, if we would let him.</p>
            <p>Had he <hi>without any tryal of Law,</hi> made <hi>his pleaſure</hi> paſs for <hi>Sentence,</hi> and lop'd off theſe <hi>rebellious Members,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Senators heads</hi> as <hi>Tarquin did Poppyes.</hi> Had he made them <hi>feel</hi> ſuch times as <hi>Tacitus</hi> deſcribes, where <hi>no man durst be vertuous</hi> leaſt he ſhould be thought to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brave <hi>his Prince;</hi> and yet to complain of their hard uſage had been Capital, and had <hi>his Subjects</hi> like <hi>Naboth been sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for their Vineyards,</hi> they might have uſed <hi>the Churches arms,</hi> Prayers and Tears, not <hi>Swords or Guns,</hi> as they did againſt him: <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>but God knows, ſo far was he from bearing juſtly the vast load and guilt of all that blood which had been ſhed in our unhappy Wars, which ſome men would needs charge upon him, to eaſe their own Souls; that he was ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more afraid, to take away any mans Life unjustly, than to loſe his own.</hi>
               </q> He <hi>reſisted our enemies to the blood,</hi> and choſe to loſe <hi>His own Head,</hi> rather than <hi>one hair</hi> ſhould fall from <hi>ours:</hi> So that next to God and his good Angels, we were <hi>most</hi> beholding to him for our ſafety. <hi>Rerum prima Salus &amp; una Caeſar.</hi> He was indeed the <hi>Tutelar Angel</hi> of his 3 Kingdoms, whom when God called to himſelf; he quickly ſent a <hi>destroying Angel</hi> among us.</p>
            <p>And yet ſuch was the <hi>touchineſs</hi> of thoſe times (and it more than begins to be the ſame in theſe) <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>that, though he intended, not only to oblige his friends, but his enemies alſo, being perſwaded that he could neither grant too much, nor diſtrust too little;</hi>
               </q> yet his matchleſs favours did rather
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101317:9"/> 
               <hi>exaſperate</hi> than <hi>win them,</hi> their poyſoned hearts turning all into venome.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Martyr</hi> ſaw it clearly before he dyed, and <hi>His Son</hi> cannot chooſe but ſee it now: that <hi>malice is not abated by time,</hi> nor appeaſed by any good turns: <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>chiav. l. 3. c. 6.</note> And that the Prince who would be wary of <hi>conſpirators,</hi> ſhould be moſt jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of thoſe, to whom he has <hi>afforded moſt ſavours.</hi> With what <hi>monſtrous ingratitude</hi> was his indulgence repayed? whilſt it forced him <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>to obſerve, that his letting ſome men go up to the pinacle of the Temple, was a temptation to them, to cast him down headlong; and that others hydropicke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiableneſs, learned to thirst the more, by how much the more they drank: in ſo much that the fountain of his Royal boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty could not ſatisfie them.</hi>
               </q> An <hi>Epidemical diſeaſe</hi> it is, which rages as much among the <hi>people of this age,</hi> as of the <hi>last.</hi> Nor is it any wonder, that he did not anſwer the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable expectations of theſe people: For the leaſt they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from him, was to <hi>ſacrifice his Honour,</hi> break his Oath, and to give up the <hi>Government,</hi> and with it, his <hi>faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt friends</hi> as a <hi>victime</hi> to the fury of his fierceſt Enemies, and to <hi>violate his conſcience</hi> in the breach of thoſe Laws, which he had ſworn to maintain; which were to have made <hi>himſelf ſecond</hi> in a fault, which the <hi>impartial world</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd in them, as the <hi>firſt</hi> and principal offenders.</p>
            <p>Caſt but an eye upon his <hi>conceſſions,</hi> and you ſhall quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceive, that never any villains were <hi>brib'd into murder,</hi> at ſo <hi>cheap a rate,</hi> and with ſo little colour of provocation as they. (I muſt always except their <hi>impenitent offſpring.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Was <hi>their quarrel</hi> commenc'd for the <hi>true Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?</hi> So was his to the death, when he prov'd himſelf to have <hi>Defender of the Faith</hi> among his Titles, more <hi>by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert</hi> than <hi>inheritance.</hi> Was it for the <hi>Priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> he thought nothing too <hi>honourable</hi> for them but <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and 'tis to be hop'd, they will be <hi>taught</hi> to be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent without that still.</hi> Did <hi>they</hi> aim at the <hi>liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject?</hi> So did <hi>He:</hi> Unleſs they meant the <hi>licentiouſneſs of the rabble,</hi> which open'd the flood-gates to that <hi>impetuous tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> which carryed down the <hi>Government of Church and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101317:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> State,</hi> of Soveraignty, Prelacy and Peerage. Did they <hi>stand up</hi> for <hi>the Laws of the Land?</hi> So did he, and <hi>fell</hi> for them too; ſo will neither <hi>they</hi> nor <hi>their offſpring</hi> do. Was it for <hi>the right adminiſtration of Juſtice?</hi> Where and when did they ever know it in <hi>greater perfection</hi> than <hi>in his Reign?</hi> If <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>plenty</hi> could have ſtop'd their mouths, Heaven had prevented their clamours againſt him: for in no Kings <hi>Reign</hi> were the <hi>Commons</hi> in greater wealth, the <hi>Nobility</hi> more honoured, or the <hi>Clergy</hi> leſs wrong'd. And if <hi>liberty of Conſcience</hi> was the thing they ſtruggled for, (the common Vouchee of all National quarrels) when he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wanted it, he was <hi>most ready to give it;</hi> and ſo might have ſaid in theſe points to them, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the reſt of the Apoſtles, <hi>that in all theſe things he had labour'd more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly than they all,</hi> for which, he will always have his <hi>Chair of State in every Loyal breaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was indeed a <hi>Prince,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 38.</note> whoſe ſupereminent Graces were ſuch, as became God's Deputy; <hi>of whom the World was not worthy,</hi> I am ſure, not theſe <hi>ingrateful Iſlands:</hi> whether he were <hi>a better King or Chriſtian, more innocent</hi> in his doing or <hi>patient</hi> in his ſufferings, is not eaſie to determine. <hi>Natus erat in Exemplar,</hi> he was born for a <hi>Preſident of goodneſs,</hi> his Great example was both a <hi>Law and a demonstration,</hi> and his <hi>chaſte life</hi> a dayly Sermon againſt his <hi>lustful Enemies.</hi> His <hi>Parts and Piety,</hi> his <hi>Reaſon and Religion</hi> were beyond any but <hi>his own expreſſion.</hi> Nor did ever <hi>any Age,</hi> ſince our Saviour's Paſſion, furniſh the World with ſo <hi>great an example</hi> of Patience and Conſtancy, as that which he this day ſet us.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould I praiſe him to you, who are ſo much the more miſerable in the loſs of him, by how much the more you knew him? What Gifts and Graces were <hi>in him,</hi> as he <hi>uſed them,</hi> ſo let <hi>us aſcribe them</hi> to the King of all Glory.</p>
            <p>We have ſeen, how ſeldom <hi>Excellency</hi> is in any Kind <hi>long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived,</hi> and how rarely the men of this World can indure any <hi>ſupereminent goodneſs.</hi> It had not elſe been poſſible for the <hi>Sons of Belial,</hi> for any but <hi>the Devil and his black Angels</hi> to have been incenſed againſt ſuch a <hi>meek and harmleſs Prince</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101317:10"/> as this, much leſs for his <hi>own Subjects</hi> to have <hi>murder'd him;</hi> for them who were <hi>hatch'd under the covert of his wings,</hi> to pick out his eyes, for ſuch <hi>Cuckows</hi> to devour him, from whom next under God, they <hi>received their well being,</hi> is a <hi>Prodigy.</hi> Cannot <hi>Caeſar</hi> be butcher'd, but <hi>Brutus</hi> muſt profer the Stab? Cannot <hi>Christ</hi> be betray'd, but one <hi>of his own Diſciples</hi> muſt be the chief Contriver? Cannot St. <hi>Steven</hi> be ſtoned, but by his <hi>Country-men?</hi> And muſt ſo <hi>Gracious a King</hi> become the <hi>white object</hi> for the <hi>ſquint-ey'd malice</hi> of his own trayterous Subjects, to dart thoſe ſpleeniſh Arrows at, which they had drawn out of the Artillery of Hell? Could there be a greater Piacle in nature? Could there be a more execrable and horrid thing? Tranſanimated Devils was a ſtranger Metempſhychoſis than ever Poets fancyed; and yet <hi>Maximilian</hi> you ſee was little leſs than a Prophet, in ſtyling the King of great <hi>Britain</hi> a Prince of Devils, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his Subjects frequent <hi>inſurrections</hi> againſt and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions</hi> of their Princes. We have had the <hi>best Kings,</hi> and been <hi>the worſt ſubjects</hi> in Chriſtendome, to <hi>our ſhame</hi> be it ſpoken.</p>
            <p>Who can <hi>ſtretch out his hand againſt the Lords Anoynted,</hi> and be innocent? Can his <hi>own Subjects</hi> do it? how came the <hi>feet</hi> by any authority, to <hi>judge the head,</hi> or <hi>ſubjects</hi> to ſit upon their <hi>Soveraign?</hi> Does the <hi>King hold this Crown</hi> by indentures from his people? As much as the <hi>Father</hi> does his Government, <hi>by a Covenant with his Children.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8. 15.</note> 'Tis <hi>by me</hi> (ſayeth God) <hi>that Kings Reign.</hi> Shall thoſe that are of his <hi>making</hi> be of the peoples marring? ſhall Children condition with their <hi>Parents</hi> upon ſuch and ſuch uſage to be acquitted of their duty and obedience? and muſt they expect to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change <hi>Authority</hi> with them? and ſhall they govern by the <hi>wills of their ſons and Servants</hi> or by their <hi>own?</hi> Of what <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted Cup</hi> had they drunk ſo deep, as to <hi>forget</hi> themſelves to be <hi>ſubjects,</hi> and that it was <hi>for them</hi> to do <hi>their duty,</hi> and the <hi>King his pleaſure?</hi> If they were <hi>above him,</hi> how <hi>was he Supreme,</hi> and how they <hi>his ſubjects?</hi> or was <hi>his ſupremacy</hi> to be torn off by the hands of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ormation,</hi> a <hi>rag of popery?</hi> or if they <hi>were his ſubjects,</hi> how came they to be <hi>his Judges?</hi> and if <hi>no judges,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101317:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> how could they be <hi>his Avengers?</hi> and if <hi>no Avengers,</hi> why were they not <hi>quiet?</hi> how durſt they lift up <hi>their hands,</hi> or indeed <hi>open their mouths</hi> againſt him? <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaid right, even in <hi>Machiavels Judgment,</hi> that men ſhould <hi>wiſh for good Princes,</hi> but <hi>whatſoever they are, indure them,</hi> and verily he who does otherwiſe (let <hi>your Whigs</hi> and <hi>our Diſſenters</hi> ſay what they pleaſe) ruines both himſelf and his Country. God made <hi>him King,</hi> and <hi>us Subjects,</hi> we were <hi>wedded together</hi> at his <hi>Coronation;</hi> and ſo we ſhould have continued <hi>like Man and Wife for better for worſe:</hi> our obedience being not to depend upon his good behaviour, but upon <hi>Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance;</hi> and yet notwithſtanding this cloſe tye of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and their manifold Obligations to him, his <hi>own Subjects,</hi> and the <hi>ſcum</hi> of them, deſtroyed him.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who were <hi>immanitate ſcelerum tuti,</hi> Secur'd by the greatneſs of their crimes, were <hi>the men</hi> who made uſe of <hi>the inſolency of the rabble,</hi> and the <hi>Midwifery of tumults</hi> to bring forth <hi>confuſion,</hi> on Church and State. They are now taking the ſame methods a ſecond time, pray God, ſend us better Succeſs. Theſe were thoſe <hi>Sainted Salamanders,</hi> who courted a <hi>combustion</hi> and a <hi>ſcramble:</hi> becauſe their <hi>fortunes</hi> were <hi>as deſperate</hi> as their <hi>deſigns;</hi> which they could not <hi>drive on</hi> without <hi>grating</hi> upon all the <hi>Extremes</hi> imaginable. It muſt be by an <hi>Error of Humanity,</hi> if we take ſuch <hi>ingrateful beasts</hi> as theſe, for <hi>men,</hi> it being directly againſt the <hi>radical principles of nature,</hi> and no leſs than a demonſtration of beſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, for any to <hi>deſtroy thoſe</hi> to whom they <hi>owe</hi> their <hi>ſelf pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation,</hi> and to ſin with ſo high an hand, againſt their <hi>principal benefactor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet if He had not been ſufficiently <hi>ſecur'd</hi> from their violence by the <hi>Law of nature,</hi> yet certainly he was by the <hi>Laws of our Nation;</hi> which have abundantly declared <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>that neither the Lords nor Commons, nor both together in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament (much leſs a Still-born houſe of Commons) not the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>collectively or repreſentatively,</hi> nor <hi>any other perſons</hi> whatſoever, have or ought to have <hi>any coercive power over</hi> the perſon of any King of our Realm:</hi>
               </q> who is ſo far <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> the <hi>Father of his Country,</hi> that a <hi>Woman</hi> may as well
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101317:11"/> 
               <hi>get a Child upon her ſelf,</hi> as <hi>both Houſes of Parliament</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any Law, till the <hi>Kings conſent</hi> firſt paſs upon them. <hi>Omnes ſub eo &amp; ipſe ſub nullo, niſi tantum ſub Deo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton,</hi> who was <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice in King Henry the thirds time;</hi> ſo that their crime was both <hi>unnatural</hi> and <hi>illegal,</hi> even by <hi>that very Law,</hi> by which they intended to hold and defend their own lives and liberties.</p>
            <p>Nay ſo it likewiſe was, by that <hi>Eternal Law of God,</hi> to which <hi>most of them</hi> have already, and the <hi>reſt</hi> muſt ere long ſubmit their ſouls; and of this I the rather ſpeak, becauſe the <hi>Devil of Rebellion transformed himſelf into an Angel of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> and is beginning to <hi>play the ſame Game</hi> over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and many were ſo <hi>deſperately ſeduced</hi> by that <hi>grand impoſtor,</hi> as to ſhake hands with their allegiance, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of laying <hi>faſter hold on Religion</hi> and Reformation; as if <hi>Chriſtian liberty</hi> did loſe the <hi>reines of civil Government,</hi> and <hi>Saintſhip</hi> give them a <hi>Priviledge</hi> againſt the <hi>intereſt of obedience:</hi> which they who undertake to maintain muſt <hi>ſharpen their Weapons, at the Philiſtines forge,</hi> go to <hi>Rome</hi> for arguments; whoſe <hi>School-men</hi> indeavouring to <hi>thruſt the King below the Pope,</hi> thought it their ſureſt way to <hi>advance the People</hi> in ſome caſes <hi>above him;</hi> theſe <hi>ſeeds of Rebellion</hi> muſt be fetch'd from their <hi>School Divinity,</hi> from whence Chriſtianity received its bane. Rebellion under pretence of Religion, is the <hi>vertical point of Jeſuitiſm,</hi> the <hi>top branch of Popery,</hi> and <hi>Jack Presbyter</hi> was over familiar with the <hi>Whore of Babylon</hi> when he <hi>stole that Doctrine</hi> out of her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; 'tis indeed more like a peice of the <hi>Alcoran</hi> than of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> an Article of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> not of the <hi>Chriſtian Creed.</hi> Let us not therefore <hi>for fear of loſing our Religion,</hi> without fear or wit, preſently <hi>jump into Rebellion:</hi> for Chriſt never taught the <hi>ſword of the Spirit,</hi> to make way to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, by <hi>cutting through the fleſh;</hi> nor did he ever <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize ſubjects</hi> to plant or water <hi>his Chriſtian Doctrine</hi> (much leſs their <hi>own phanatical deviſes</hi>) in the <hi>blood of their Soveraign, and fellow Subjects.</hi> He mentions ſome who <hi>took the Kingdom of Heaven by violence,</hi> not any who by <hi>violence impoſed</hi> it <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others.</hi> Nay the <hi>Prophet</hi> tells the <hi>Jewes,</hi> that in <hi>the day when
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101317:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> they found themſelves oppreſſed by their King, they ſhould cry out for redreſs unto the Lord,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 17. 18.</note> as the only Arbiter and Judge of the Deeds of Princes, <hi>againſt whom there is no riſing up;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 30. 31.</note> and when the <hi>Jews</hi> asked Chriſt, <hi>whether they ſhould pay Tribute to</hi> Caeſar <hi>or not?</hi> de did not ask them, whether there were <hi>any Statute</hi> againſt it, nor adviſe them to <hi>defer their payment</hi> till <hi>the People</hi> ſhould agree upon it: he only looked upon the <hi>Superſcription of the money,</hi> and told them <hi>to whom it was due;</hi> and his <hi>practice</hi> was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to it, when he choſe rather to <hi>fiſh for money,</hi> and to be at the expence of a Miracle to <hi>pay his Taxes,</hi> than to offend the Higher Powers. And that he might teach <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> to the <hi>worſt of Kings,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 11.</note> he acknowledges even <hi>Pilate's Power to be of God;</hi> this I am ſure was the <hi>Judgment of Chriſt,</hi> and the former of one who <hi>lived long before Antichriſt.</hi> Our bleſſed Saviour <hi>obeyed unto death,</hi> under the Reign of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> and his Diſciples under <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, Claudius</hi> and <hi>Caligula.</hi> And when <hi>Julian</hi> from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity fell to <hi>flat Paganiſm,</hi> you ſhall find the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> whom he loaded with Perſecutions, not entring into any <hi>Rebellious Aſſociations,</hi> but fitting their <hi>Necks to his Yoak,</hi> and teaching one another <hi>poſtures,</hi> how they might <hi>ſtand faireſt</hi> for the ſtroke of death: and that, not becauſe they <hi>could not help themſelves</hi> (for the greateſt part of his Army were then <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) but becauſe they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, that no man could become a <hi>Traytor,</hi> who had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>relick of Grace</hi> in him; and that he who ſhakes off this <hi>Sacred Bond</hi> of Obedience, hath firſt <hi>reſigned Heaven,</hi> and <hi>made ſhipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience.</hi> He who faltreth in his Allegiance to the <hi>King the Deputy,</hi> does <hi>manifeſtly revolt</hi> from <hi>God the Deputer.</hi> If the King oppreſs his Subjects, 'tis the <hi>abuſing</hi> of that Power <hi>which is in him,</hi> which is to be reſerved for a Divine Judgment; but if the People <hi>take up Arms,</hi> 'tis an <hi>uſurping of that Power which belongs not to them,</hi> an Act of <hi>Injuſtice</hi> againſt God, an <hi>invading the Right and Prerogative of Heaven,</hi> and a leavying War againſt <hi>God's Ordinance;</hi> which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101317:12"/> ceaſes not to be <hi>Sacred</hi> when 'tis <hi>wickedly imployed;</hi> and for this, God hath appointed <hi>the King</hi> to puniſh them, and not to <hi>bear the Sword in vain.</hi> And he took the <hi>Kingdom from</hi> Saul, not for being <hi>too tyrannical to his Subjects,</hi> but for being <hi>too merciful to his Enemies,</hi> in ſparing <hi>Agag;</hi> Let all <hi>Crowned heads</hi> take that for a <hi>warning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet this was <hi>no rub</hi> at all in our <hi>home-bred Rebels way,</hi> who had neither <hi>Faith</hi> enough to make them <hi>true Chriſtians,</hi> nor yet <hi>ſo much Hypocriſie,</hi> as to make them <hi>plauſibly ſeem ſo:</hi> (and yet they had <hi>more</hi> of that, than <hi>did themſelves or others good</hi> too, and ſo have their <hi>Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring</hi>) for after they had <hi>ſworn Subjection</hi> to him and his Heirs, in the <hi>Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance,</hi> and in <hi>another</hi> which deſerves to be <hi>named no more</hi> amongſt us, being firſt <hi>unlawfully taken,</hi> and after, more <hi>unlawfully kept</hi> by too many, after all the <hi>complicated Proteſtations</hi> of the ſincerity of their intentions to him, they <hi>perſidiouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed</hi> him; <hi>Judas</hi> was juſt ſuch another <hi>Saint</hi> as they, and much <hi>of their complexion and perſwaſion.</hi> There was not a <hi>Petition,</hi> not a <hi>Meſſage,</hi> not a <hi>Declaration</hi> they ever ſent him, in which they did not <hi>oblige themſelves by the Faith of Chriſtians</hi> (they meant of <hi>Devils,</hi> who never keep their words but in malice) to have <hi>a tender regard for his Sacred Perſon,</hi> and to make him <hi>a great and glorious King;</hi> and yet they were never ſo good as their words, till they firſt <hi>platted him a Crown of Thorns,</hi> and then made his way to a <hi>Crown of Eternal Glory:</hi> one would think, they ſtill had ſuch another <hi>under the Anvil,</hi> for <hi>his Son.</hi> How much <hi>reſpect</hi> ſoever they acknowledged to be <hi>due,</hi> they never <hi>paid him any;</hi> unleſs like the <hi>worſhippers of Hermes,</hi> they thought the <hi>hurling ſtones at him</hi> to be the beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of their devotion. Their <hi>Trojan horſes</hi> which they ſent him, were conſecrated indeed to <hi>Pallas without,</hi> but lined with an ambuſh of <hi>armed Enemies</hi> within; and their <hi>foul Projects</hi> the more horrid, for having ſuch a <hi>diſguizing luster</hi> perpetually put upon them. Was the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to which, they pretended ſuch a zeal, <hi>to bring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101317:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> him,</hi> held at <hi>Holmby houſe,</hi> or at <hi>Carisbrook caſtle?</hi> Was S. <hi>James's,</hi> the <hi>High Court of Juſtice,</hi> or the <hi>Scaffold</hi> the <hi>place</hi> in which they meant <hi>to debate with him?</hi> Did ever men give themſelves <hi>the lye</hi> ſo loudly, as theſe? Or did they ever mean (do you think?) to <hi>run the hazard</hi> of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>honeſt,</hi> whilſt ſuch <hi>down right knavery</hi> as this would ſerve their turns. Their wickedneſs was not <hi>ſpun with ſo fine a thread,</hi> but that it might be diſcovered; nor have they taught <hi>their Children</hi> to mend the matter. They had better have uſed <hi>no pretences</hi> at all, for their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, then ſuch <hi>frivolous</hi> ones as they did: ſo eaſily was their <hi>nakedneſs</hi> betrayed <hi>through their fig-leaves,</hi> when they thought they had ſtitcht them together to the greateſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. We do not now want ſufficient evidence to prove that <hi>Rebellion</hi> may be in <hi>Maſkarade,</hi> aſwel as <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> which hath two <hi>holes to his den,</hi> can <hi>ſtop</hi> or open <hi>either,</hi> as the Weather ſits, and they commenced their quarrel ſo cunningly, that as their <hi>intereſſed zeal</hi> taught them to <hi>clip the King in ſunder</hi> by a <hi>State distincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> ſeperating <hi>his Perſon</hi> from <hi>his Power;</hi> ſo that they might the better <hi>diſguiſe</hi> their more dangerous ſecret, they made <hi>the ſpecious pretence</hi> of fighting <hi>againſt his Evil Councillers,</hi> to ſtalk before it. And who would not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly offer himſelf a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to ſo good a Cauſe? Who would not lift up his hand againſt them who <hi>intend any Evil to my Lord the King,</hi> either in his <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> if <hi>his Sacred Life</hi> be in danger, all good Subjects will <hi>hazard theirs</hi> to ſave it. Theſe were thoſe <hi>words of Inchantment,</hi> by which the <hi>unthinking people</hi> were ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſually enticed into their own Thraldom, and a great part of that <hi>diſmal ſpell,</hi> which raiſed the <hi>Spirit of diſcord,</hi> to walk ſo long among them; and I pray God he be not conjured again by the ſame methods.</p>
            <p>But alas, how ſoon was <hi>this Mask of Hypocriſie</hi> laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and the <hi>face</hi> of their dark deſign overſpread with a <hi>Rebellious Leproſie?</hi> How ſoon was <hi>Jacob's voyce</hi> betrayed by the palpable roughneſs of <hi>Eſau's hands?</hi> Was there
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101317:13"/> 
               <hi>any one motive</hi> by which they were <hi>induced to ſight,</hi> made good? And which I pray of his <hi>Evil Councillers,</hi> when they had Him in their power, did they labour to deſtroy, unleſs they took his <hi>Good Conſcience</hi> for one?</p>
            <p>But when <hi>Faction</hi> hath <hi>bent her bow,</hi> ſhe never wants ſome <hi>Bolts to ſhoot;</hi> they who <hi>reſolve</hi> to <hi>pick quarrels,</hi> know at leaſt, how to <hi>feign ſuſpicions</hi> and jealouſies, and upon no better foundation than this did they raiſe the quarrel: ſo that the <hi>King's real wrong</hi> was to joyn battle with their <hi>weak ſurmizes;</hi> for the <hi>Injury and Invaſion,</hi> of which they complained, was only <hi>contingent and conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral;</hi> a Plot wrapt up in the womb of ſome <hi>dark Cabinet Councils,</hi> which engaged them by a <hi>Preventive</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipating War,</hi> to take up Arms againſt the King, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he was,</hi> but becauſe he poſſibly <hi>might be a Tyrant:</hi> which that they might the better induce the <hi>credulous ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> to believe; they dealt with their minds, as <hi>melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men</hi> uſe to do with <hi>the Clouds,</hi> raiſed monſtrous forms and ſhapes to fright them, where no fear was, as <hi>Time,</hi> (the beſt Interpreter of mens intentions) did <hi>convince us.</hi> By ſuch <hi>black Arts</hi> did they raiſe up thoſe <hi>turbulent Spirits,</hi> which they would afterwards, have been glad they could have <hi>conjured down</hi> again; but <hi>armed Petitioners</hi> were not ſo eaſily <hi>disbanded</hi> as liſted.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>ſecurity</hi> conſiſted in <hi>ſcaring the People,</hi> who are a ſort of <hi>timerous Dear,</hi> and as wild as Bucks, whoſe <hi>heads</hi> when they are once <hi>fly-blown</hi> with the buzzes of ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the <hi>Vermin</hi> multiply exceedingly, and <hi>one jealouſie</hi> begets <hi>another.</hi> Many were the <hi>Birds of prey</hi> which they <hi>threw off</hi> from their fiſts, to devour his reputation; (the ſame which now fly at <hi>his Son's, our Gracious Sovereign</hi>) the <hi>place</hi> of whoſe breeding was ſo well known, that they might have ventured to have floun them <hi>without varvels,</hi> for their <hi>owners</hi> might have been found in S. <hi>Stevens Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> without the help of <hi>a cunning man.</hi> Lord, what weak, groundleſs and <hi>improbable conjectures</hi> did they raiſe, of the <hi>King's adherence to the Church of Rome?</hi> And how many
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101317:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuch <hi>baſtard creatures</hi> of their own corrupt fancies did they <hi>lay to his charge?</hi> As if it had been part of their <hi>Religion</hi> to <hi>revile him:</hi> whereas if they would have ſpoke <hi>their conſcience,</hi> and not <hi>their ſpleen,</hi> they muſt needs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that, He had <hi>done more</hi> for the <hi>ſuppreſſion of Popery,</hi> than any <hi>Prince</hi> before him. Witneſs his Anſwer to the <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>OXON</hi> in the <hi>firſt year</hi> of his Reign, concerning the ſuppreſſion of Popery <hi>A.D.</hi> 1625. To the Petition of the Third Parliament, <hi>A.D.</hi> 1628. and his <hi>Proclamation,</hi> in farther purſuance of it, 3. <hi>Aug. An. Reg. quarte.</hi> Witneſs his <hi>Confirmation</hi> of the <hi>third Canon</hi> made in the Convocation, <hi>A.D.</hi> 1640. for ſuppreſſing of the growth of Popery. Witneſs his <hi>Proteſtation</hi> which he made near <hi>Wellington,</hi> in the County of <hi>Stafford.</hi> 19. <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temb.</hi> 1642. Whereby he ingaged himſelf in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Almighty God, to live and die (as he did) in the true Proteſtant Religion, as it ſtood in its Beauty in the happy days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> without any connivance at Popery, and to the utmoſt of his power defend and maintain it. Witneſs his <hi>Confirmation</hi> of that his <hi>Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> before his receiving of the Holy Euchariſt at <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>OXON, A.D.</hi> 1643. and his Latine Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it to all Forreign Churches in <hi>May</hi> 1644. and his <hi>Conference</hi> with the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi> at <hi>Ragland Caſtle, A.D.</hi> 1645. And yet for all this, the <hi>Popular Maxime</hi> prevailed, That, <hi>the King was not to be truſted;</hi> and ſo 'twas <hi>his,</hi> 'tis <hi>his Sons</hi> and the miſery of the <hi>beſt Princes,</hi> when they <hi>do well,</hi> to be <hi>evil ſpoken of;</hi> Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelf was <hi>crowned</hi> with <hi>reproaches</hi> aſwel as <hi>thorns,</hi> and <hi>if theſe things were done in the green Tree, what ſhall be done in the dry?</hi> No wonder if they <hi>whet their Tongues like a Sword,</hi> and <hi>ſhoot for their Arrows</hi> ſuch <hi>bitter words</hi> as theſe againſt the King, <note place="margin">Pſal. 64. 3. Pſal. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> who was ſo <hi>upright in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their <hi>Antimonarchical Spirits</hi> had fill'd them ſo <hi>brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> of gall and venome againſt the <hi>Crown,</hi> that it was not ſtrange, their <hi>mouths</hi> ſhould run over, with ſuch <hi>poyſon of Aſpes,</hi> againſt the <hi>perſon of the King.</hi> Alas they ſet
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101317:14"/> their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>its</hi> on <hi>tenter-books,</hi> to find out matter of accuſation, prying into every corner for an <hi>imputation</hi> whereby they might with ſome colour <hi>beſpatter him</hi> and <hi>lay his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the duſt,</hi> making it their buſineſs to load him with <hi>dirt</hi> before the people, becauſe they <hi>hated</hi> to <hi>ſee him clean,</hi> and why did they <hi>hate</hi> him but becauſe they had <hi>abuſed him? Naturale eſt ediſſe, quem laeferis,</hi> and muſt heap injuries on whom they had wrong'd, that the <hi>latter</hi> might add ſome countenance to the <hi>former.</hi> And this was that <hi>ſeale of degrees,</hi> by which they aſcended to <hi>his Murder,</hi> as the Jews did to <hi>S. Stephens. Nemo repente fuit turpiſſimus,</hi> firſt they <hi>diſputed with him:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Uſ. 9.</note> (ſo they did with the <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> about Prerogative and Property) then they <hi>deſpiſed him,</hi> and at laſt they <hi>deſtroyed him;</hi> they <hi>begun with arguments and concluded with ſtones:</hi> ſome few perhaps there were to <hi>pitty,</hi> but none to <hi>protect him:</hi> And ſuch was their <hi>matchleſs malice</hi> to our <hi>Martyr'd Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign,</hi> whom they deſtroyed by <hi>piece meale</hi> as if they had intended, not to <hi>cut off</hi> but to <hi>unravel</hi> the thred of his life. God ſend <hi>his Son our Gracious Soveraign,</hi> fewer Enemies and more Friends, than his Father; and <hi>us,</hi> no more ſuch <hi>fatal days,</hi> as this in our Kalendar. They <hi>ſtript</hi> him in his <hi>own perſon,</hi> of all the <hi>uſual comforts</hi> of his life, burying him alive, among Seas and Rocks, <hi>hunting him as a partridge on the mountains</hi> in continual danger, hurrying him to and fro from <hi>one priſon to another,</hi> and thereby depriving him of his <hi>natural liberty</hi> as he was a <hi>man;</hi> of the Society of his Loyal and <hi>Deareſt Conſort,</hi> as he was an <hi>Husband;</hi> of the Converſation of <hi>his Children,</hi> as he was a Father; of the Attendance of his <hi>Servants,</hi> as he was a <hi>Maſter;</hi> of his <hi>Chaplains,</hi> as he was a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> of his faithful <hi>Counſellers</hi> when he moſt <hi>needed and deſired</hi> them; of his <hi>Crown, Sword</hi> and <hi>Scepter,</hi> even of all his Royal Prerogatives, as he was a King, <hi>Et quid plus velit ira?</hi> They depriv'd him of <hi>all comforts</hi> which he could poſſibly miſs, but that of a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> which was out of their reach, (afflictions <hi>ſo ſharp</hi> that <hi>no patience</hi> but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101317:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>his</hi> could have conquer'd them) carrying Swords in <hi>their mouths</hi> againſt his reputation, aſwell as in <hi>their hands</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his perſon, and all who durſt be guilty of ſo much Loyaltyas to attend or aſſiſt him, plundering him of all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, which might make <hi>life valuable</hi> for a bleſſing; and then to complete thoſe calamities into which the <hi>Elder faction</hi> had thus accurſedly plung'd him, the <hi>Younger</hi> proceeded on this <hi>diſmal day,</hi> to the utmoſt eſſay of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, they <hi>murder'd him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ended <hi>his</hi> Paſſion, this continued <hi>ours,</hi> till Our <hi>Soveraign's miraculous Reſtauration,</hi> and that eſpecially conſidering with how <hi>much</hi> heat and boldneſs and with how <hi>little remorſe</hi> they did it, not ruining him by <hi>accident</hi> and beſides their intention, but with <hi>propenſed malice.</hi> It was <hi>no fault</hi> nor <hi>vertue</hi> of theirs, that their <hi>bullets</hi> did not diſpatch him before in the battle, if Providence had not to a miracle ſecured him, he had fallen long before by their Swords, but ſeeing that would not do, they took farther council and reſolv'd at laſt upon that <hi>horrid,</hi> that <hi>bold</hi> and <hi>inſolent ſin,</hi> which we are now met as becomes us, to <hi>lament;</hi> and indeed <hi>we</hi> have the more cauſe to <hi>lament it,</hi> becauſe <hi>they did not,</hi> but with an <hi>inhumane delight</hi> and oſtentation <hi>prided</hi> themſelves in the performance of it, and though <hi>a deed of the greateſt darkneſs,</hi> the fouleſt of crimes, yet ſo ſtrangely were their <hi>conſciences ſtupified,</hi> that they committed it <hi>preſumptuouſly</hi> with an unheard of <hi>impudence,</hi> at <hi>noon day,</hi> in the ſight of the Sun, without any care to cover the <hi>conſpicuous marks</hi> of their own ſhame. <hi>Faux</hi> would have ſmotherd it in a <hi>dark Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn,</hi> and hatch'd that <hi>plot</hi> in a <hi>Celler</hi> which they brought forth upon <hi>an open ſtage.</hi> Nay they made the <hi>Place of his Royalty</hi> the <hi>Seat of his Execution,</hi> they conducted him through <hi>his greateſt room of ſtate</hi> to that <hi>bloody Theatre of inhumanity,</hi> and murdered him on <hi>a Scaffold before the gates of his own Royal Palace:</hi> ſo far did the Devil prevail with the <hi>Ambitious humour</hi> of thoſe <hi>irreligious miſcreants</hi> to drive on ſuch <hi>prodigious</hi> and prepoſterous purpoſes.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:101317:15"/>
            <p>Nay <hi>ſo hot</hi> was their <hi>Zeal,</hi> and ſo <hi>cold</hi> their <hi>charity,</hi> that he muſt dye the <hi>third day</hi> after his Sentence; a <hi>ſhort time</hi> for a King <hi>to ſet his houſe in order,</hi> and to take his leave of three Kingdoms; and a ſhorter for ſo <hi>Notorious a ſinner</hi> (as they would have made the world believe he was) to repent in. But perſecutors are always <hi>in haſte,</hi> they will neither tarry God's nor the King's leiſure, <hi>their feet are ſwift to ſhed-blood,</hi> nor can they <hi>ſleep</hi> till thoſe that offend them <hi>have ſlept the ſleep of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay that which does yet more <hi>inflame</hi> and <hi>aggravate</hi> their ſin, extracting out of <hi>it</hi> the <hi>quinteſſence of Villany,</hi> is this, that <hi>Juſtice it ſelf</hi> was courted in a complement to own it, and his <hi>Judges</hi> (who were alſo his profeſs'd Enemies, and perſecutors) <hi>cloath'd in Scarlet,</hi> that the people might the more admire them; it was done with a <hi>mock ſhew</hi> of pretended Law, and <hi>the blood-thirſty Repreſentatives</hi> indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to make their <hi>fond admirers</hi> believe, that they took council of none but of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> for the management of this their <hi>Succeſsful treaſon.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 91: 5.</note> Becauſe none of the <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gittae volantes;</hi> thoſe arrows which for their <hi>ſpeedy Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> are ſaid <hi>to fly by day,</hi> did <hi>pierce</hi> them in their Villanies, as they had done <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphyra,</hi> who only liv'd to hear of their ſins and immediately to dye for them; ſome <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolved men</hi> of little loyalty and leſs Religion were tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Cato</hi> to queſtion, and others with <hi>Diagoras</hi> to deny an over-ruling Providence, and to ſay as <hi>Diogenes</hi> did of <hi>Harpalus</hi> a notorious but proſperous thief, that it did <note place="margin">Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de. nat. Dei.</note> 
               <hi>Teſtimonium adverſus Deum dicere,</hi> ſtand up as a Witneſs againſt the <hi>all-ſeeing eye</hi> of Heaven, and they themſelves <hi>gave out</hi> that <hi>God owned their proceeding,</hi> becauſe <hi>ſwift de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> was not the immediate <hi>cataſtrophe</hi> of their diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, nor did God preſently ariſe, to vindicate the <hi>Kings injur'd innocence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They would have made men believe that they could not <hi>follow their Saviour</hi> without <hi>forſaking their Soveraign,</hi> and that they were <hi>inſpir'd</hi> to murder him; they firſt <hi>ſeek God,</hi> and then they <hi>find it expedient, to ſlay his Vicegerent,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:101317:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> which was <hi>megiſton Adikema,</hi> the greateſt villany, of which men have been guilty, for above 1600 years; and thoſe who ſwam to their <hi>deſired Haven,</hi> in ſuch a full <hi>ſtream of Royal Blood,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be <hi>ſtigmatized,</hi> at leaſt once a year, for ſuch their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious and unparallel'd Enormities.</p>
            <p>And yet the <hi>Grand Actors</hi> in this our <hi>National Tragedy,</hi> were all this while the <hi>greateſt Pretenders</hi> in the World to <hi>Loyalty and Religion;</hi> which ſet them up with ſuch a <hi>ſtock of Reputation,</hi> that upon the bare <hi>credit</hi> thereof they might run freely <hi>on the ſcore,</hi> to the commiſſion of ſuch horrid Crimes againſt both the King and the People, and yet not have their names once <hi>called to an account</hi> for any injuſtice. But we have too much cauſe to ſay of the <hi>Spawn</hi> of theſe <hi>Blood-ſuckers,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49. 7.</note> as <hi>Jacob</hi> did of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi, Curſed be their Anger, for it was fierce, and their Wrath for it was cruel;</hi> I mean the <hi>Worſhippers</hi> of that <hi>Scythian Diana,</hi> which was once <hi>fed</hi> with ſo many <hi>inhumane Sacrifices,</hi> and to which, as to another <hi>Molock,</hi> ſo many <hi>men of Parts and Piety,</hi> of Courage and Loyalty (aſwel as <hi>Children</hi>) were <hi>compelled to paſs through the fire.</hi> Not to ſwim along with the ſtream of their Rebellion, was preſent drowning, <hi>Crede, aut jugulum dabis,</hi> might have been their <hi>Motto,</hi> conſidering how many mens <hi>lives</hi> and <hi>fortunes</hi> were ſacrificed to their revenge and paſſion; there was <hi>no need nor noiſe of liberty of conſcience</hi> when that <hi>Religion</hi> was rampant. Now if theſe were <hi>Saints,</hi> who were <hi>Scythians?</hi> If theſe were the <hi>Children of God,</hi> which are the <hi>Sons of Belial?</hi> If theſe were the <hi>Failings of the Righteous,</hi> which are the <hi>Crimes of the Wicked?</hi> Let them <hi>wipe their mouths</hi> as clear as they can, they were <hi>taken bloody handed,</hi> and their treachery deſerves to travel in a Proverb to the end of the World, till they can <hi>waſh either their hands or mouths in innocence</hi> from this great Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. Some of the more <hi>moderate men</hi> (if indeed there can be <hi>any moderation</hi> in Rebellion) perhaps if they had not found it eaſier to <hi>lay on their Hounds</hi> than to <hi>rate them off,</hi> would have deſiſted ſooner, but yet they remembred ſo much of their <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Piety,</hi> (I mean of <hi>Machiavel's Inſtructions</hi>) that they would neither ſtand, <hi>ſo cloſe to the King</hi> (as well as they lov'd him) as to be <hi>oppreſſed with his ruine,</hi> nor yet <hi>ſo far off,</hi> but that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101317:16"/> when <hi>his ruine</hi> came, they might be able <hi>to riſe upon ſome parts</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>They pretended to <hi>deſerve</hi> aſwel of the <hi>Traytors and Uſurpers</hi> then, as they do now of the <hi>King,</hi> and as <hi>Godly</hi> as they were, the <hi>Crown and Church-lands,</hi> were a <hi>great Gain</hi> to them; they thought it a <hi>mortal ſin</hi> to <hi>rob</hi> either, but not ſo much as a <hi>venial</hi> one to <hi>buy the ſtollen goods.</hi> But to think that any <hi>Reaſons of mine,</hi> or <hi>Convictions of their own,</hi> ſhould make them believe, that <hi>this ſin might be laid to their charge,</hi> were to entertain a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opinion of <hi>their Piety,</hi> and <hi>my own Parts,</hi> than either of them deſerve.</p>
            <p>Never was any <hi>Parricide</hi> committed with ſo <hi>high an hand,</hi> as this, it was done by the joynt agreement and contrivance of the <hi>two Imps of Rebellion,</hi> thoſe <hi>Brethren in iniquity,</hi> whom <hi>Faction coupled,</hi> and <hi>Intereſt divided:</hi> for they <hi>ſtrugled together</hi> in the <hi>Womb of Ambition,</hi> till the <hi>elder</hi> was indeed craftily <hi>ſupplanted</hi> by the <hi>younger,</hi> who carried away the <hi>long expected Fruits</hi> of the others Plots and Practices.</p>
            <p>This made them ſo <hi>very buſie</hi> when the work was over, to <hi>ſhift off the guilt</hi> of this execrable Act, from the <hi>one</hi> to the <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and whether of the <hi>two Harlots</hi> was indeed the true <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of this <hi>Monſtrous Birth,</hi> you will beſt know by attempting to <hi>divide it. Solomon</hi> would have judged it to belong to her who would rather <hi>part with it all,</hi> than accept of <hi>half,</hi> and then the <hi>Elder Brother</hi> is the principal Murderer. Their caſe in ſhort was this; The <hi>One</hi> granted <hi>Commiſſions</hi> to fight againſt the King, but yet they would be thought to have provided for <hi>his Perſonal Safety,</hi> in a Parentheſis of fair Words, they could not ſleep in their Beds for fear of the King's being murdered, and the other judged it as lawful to <hi>behead</hi> him. The <hi>one</hi> gave the <hi>Council,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> the <hi>Stroke.</hi> The <hi>one</hi> laid the <hi>Train,</hi> and the <hi>other fired</hi> it. The <hi>one</hi> devoured the <hi>Prey,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> gave a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> to it. The <hi>one</hi> carried on the Rebellion in the four firſt Acts of the Tragedy, and the <hi>other</hi> were the bloody performers of the fifth. The <hi>one ſharpned the Ax,</hi> and the <hi>other ſtroke</hi> with it. The <hi>one brought his Royal head to the block,</hi> and the <hi>other ſevered it</hi> from his ſhoulders. The <hi>elder</hi> of the Twins
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101317:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>bound his</hi> Father, and the Younger <hi>butchered</hi> him. The <hi>one</hi> firſt murdered <hi>the King of Great Brittain,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> the <hi>Perſon of Charles the Firſt, Vel neutrum flammis ure, vel ure duos,</hi> they run at leaſt <hi>parcel guilty,</hi> and both of them certainly <hi>waſhed their hands in his blood,</hi> how deſirous ſoever they have been ſince to <hi>waſh them of it:</hi> But to whether of the two, the <hi>ſin</hi> is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly chargeable, I had rather, a better Caſuiſt would reſolve them. Between them I am ſure, they have brought the <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſcandal</hi> upon the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> imaginable, making it as much <hi>the Scorn and Reproach,</hi> as before it was the <hi>Envy and Glory of the World.</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Pudet haec opprobria nobis,</l>
                  <l>Et dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe refelli.</l>
               </q> God grant, <hi>our Poſterity</hi> may learn to be <hi>aſhamed</hi> of thoſe Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which have brought ſuch an <hi>obloquy and diſgrace</hi> upon us, as to make us the ſole object of <hi>publick execrations</hi> and curſes.</p>
            <p>And that eſpecially conſidering, what a <hi>vaſt Treaſure</hi> they ſquandred away, to purchaſe <hi>his deſtruction,</hi> who was the chief Inſtrument of <hi>their preſervation,</hi> and in fine their <hi>own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> too, for <hi>Quid tu ſi peream ego?</hi> What became of the <hi>Peerage,</hi> when <hi>Prelacy</hi> and <hi>Kingſhip</hi> were run down? Then was a time when <hi>Actaeon-like</hi> they were worried by <hi>their own Hounds,</hi> till they had learned that, <hi>Nemo gratis malus est,</hi> that they had bought their iniquity at a dear rate; and better they had <hi>never been born,</hi> than that the <hi>guilt of</hi> their iniquity ſhould lie ſo heavy upon them, and the <hi>puniſhment</hi> devolve, as it did, upon ſo many thouſands beſides them.</p>
            <p>But like <hi>blind Sampſon,</hi> ſo they gratified their own <hi>revenge,</hi> they were utterly regardleſs <hi>how many they deſtroyed,</hi> in plucking down the glorious Fabrick of Church and State about their ears. <hi>No calling</hi> drank ſo deep of this <hi>bitter cup,</hi> in that unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural War as <hi>ours,</hi> the <hi>States</hi> loſs was not to be <hi>expreſſed,</hi> but <hi>the Churches</hi> not to be <hi>imagined:</hi> for <hi>our Priviledges and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues</hi> were not only taken from us, by thoſe Jews, who would have <hi>Crucified Chriſt himſelf</hi> (as they did his Vicegerent) <hi>to get
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101317:17"/> his Garments,</hi> but <hi>our office</hi> it ſelf lay ableeding, and was draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to its laſt gaſp, if a <hi>Miracle of Providence,</hi> had not ſent us <hi>ſuch a Sovereign,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Nurſing Father,</hi> as God hath now bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed us with, to revive it.</p>
            <p>Now if when ſo many <hi>frightful circumſtances</hi> meet together, to wring tears from our eyes, at the <hi>reſentment</hi> of ſuch an <hi>incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable loſs,</hi> do not ingage us in a ſerious lamentation, and if our ſobbs do not grave the <hi>remembrance</hi> of our Martyr'd Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign in our hearts, in <hi>Characters as great,</hi> as was the <hi>Crime of His Murderers,</hi> we are more inſenſible of <hi>God's Dealings,</hi> and our <hi>own Demerits,</hi> then becomes us.</p>
            <p>There were more <hi>Judaſes</hi> than one, who <hi>Sinned in betraying this Innocent Blood.</hi> I wiſh they had learned ſo much <hi>ingenuity</hi> from him as to confeſs it, and ſo much <hi>wiſdom</hi> from God's long ſuffering, as to ſee it betimes, not dreaming that, a <hi>general guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> will amount to <hi>Innocence in Heaven,</hi> as it does ſometimes on Earth. I ſhall deſerve your <hi>pardon,</hi> if I value <hi>your Souls,</hi> which coſt the <hi>Blood of Chriſt</hi> at more than a words ſpeaking, There being no flattery ſo fatal, as that of the <hi>Phyſician</hi> and the <hi>Divine.</hi> I ſhall eſteem your <hi>amendment</hi> ſo much above your <hi>favour,</hi> as to have more reſpect to <hi>your happineſs,</hi> than to ſuffer you to live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer in <hi>a miſtaken opinion,</hi> of your <hi>own innocence,</hi> even as to this Crime. And what I ſpeak in <hi>this place,</hi> will I hope, be the better taken, becauſe 'tis out of a <hi>deſire to convince all;</hi> and not <hi>to ſhame any of you;</hi> unleſs I ſhame <hi>ſome few by accident,</hi> in refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the glory of true Repentance; for I am fully perſwaded that the <hi>major part of you</hi> are already ſatisfied that you can never be <hi>ſenſible enough, nor repent too much</hi> of this ſin.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore, not any longer <hi>inveigh</hi> againſt thoſe <hi>notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Villains,</hi> whoſe faults are written in their fore heads, but come by a <hi>particular ſerutiny</hi> to enquire into <hi>our ſelves,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>we</hi> can plead <hi>not guilty</hi> to that Crime, for which we have heard them indited; and ſhall not rather be forced to ſay with <hi>Aeneas,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Et quorum pars magna fui.</l>
               </q> That we have a <hi>great ſhare</hi> in his Iniquity.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101317:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> There is no beguiling of the pangs of our own Conſciences.
<q>
                  <l>Haret lateri lethalis arundo.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>guilt</hi> will ſtick <hi>as cloſe to us</hi> as <hi>Deianiras</hi> poyſoned ſhirt did to <hi>Hercules.</hi> Let us therefore <hi>have mercy</hi> on our Souls, and not be ſo <hi>deſperately fooliſh,</hi> as to flatter them unto deſtruction</p>
            <p>'Twas the <hi>wickedneſs of our Sodom,</hi> which provoked God <hi>to ſend his Angel,</hi> to fetch that <hi>righteous Lot from among us;</hi> and had we kept <hi>God's Commandments</hi> better, we might have kept <hi>his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent</hi> longer: who like an <hi>abuſed mercy,</hi> was in great Juſtice taken from us, upon which we may uſe the Prophet's language, <note place="margin">Dan. 9. 12.</note> 
               <hi>And he hath confirm'd his words which he ſpake againſt us, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Judges that Judged us, by bringing upon us a great plague, for under the whole Heaven hath not been the like, that hath been brought upon our Hieruſalem.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 9. 7.</note> 
               <hi>O lord, righteouſneſs belongeth unto thee, and to us open ſhame, as appears this day.</hi> Had we not lull'd our ſelves aſleep in the <hi>boſome of thoſe vices,</hi> to which our ſouls were ſo affectionately wedded, but writ them a <hi>bill of divorce,</hi> and not ſuffer'd them to come any more under our roofs, God would never have <hi>viſited us</hi> with ſo ſevere a chaſtiſement; But let the burn'd Children dread the fire, <hi>for if ye do wickedly, you ſhall be deſtroyed both you and your King,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 25.</note> and if <hi>we ſay that we did not</hi> and do not ſo ſtill, <hi>we deceive our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I doubt <hi>this Sin</hi> may be lay'd to ſome of <hi>your charges</hi> much <hi>nearer</hi> then ſo, who might be partakers of it, ſome of theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>Conſent and approbation,</hi> or <hi>taking pleaſure</hi> in them who did it. Thus, if <hi>many</hi> people by <hi>joynt conſent</hi> ſet upon a man and Kill him, though <hi>one</hi> only give him the deadly wound, yet they <hi>all</hi> are guilty of the murder, becauſe they <hi>all intended</hi> it, <hi>did ſomething</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it: for <hi>their number</hi> was the cauſe of <hi>his terror,</hi> and of the abatement of his courage, and an occaſion to make him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of defending himſelf, and by conſequence <hi>that terrour</hi> was the cauſe of his receiving his wounds, and the <hi>wounds</hi> the cauſe of his death, and ſo <hi>their malice</hi> is to be <hi>judged equal</hi> by their conjunct attempt. Thus <hi>Saul</hi> was guilty of <hi>St. Stephen's death;</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:101317:18"/> Thus <hi>thouſands</hi> were of Our Soveraign's, even as many as ever <hi>drew their Swords,</hi> nay as ever <hi>opened their mouths</hi> or <hi>purſes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By <hi>Council and Advice,</hi> for <hi>Qui monet quaſi adjuvat;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 11. 49.</note> ſo <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iaphas</hi> had a hand in the blood of our Crucifyed Saviour; ſo as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as <hi>inſtigated, encouraged,</hi> or <hi>abetted the rebellion,</hi> had, in the blood of our Martyr'd Soveraign.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By appointment and command, ſo <hi>Pharoah</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> ſlew <hi>the infants;</hi> ſo <hi>David, Uriah;</hi> ſo theſe <hi>infernal Judges</hi> did the King.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By <hi>Commending, Applauding, Defending, or Excuſing the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> for <hi>woe be to them who call evil good, who put light for darkneſs and ſweet for bitter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. By <hi>partaking with his murderers, in the fruits of their Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 5. 20.</note> and ſo all <hi>ſequeſtrators, commitee men</hi> and <hi>purchaſers</hi> of the <hi>Crown or Church</hi> lands were guilty.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By <hi>concealing the treaſon</hi> when it was hatching; for as good <hi>lay thy hand on the Lords anointed,</hi> as <hi>lay thy hand on thy mouth</hi> and conceal the treaſon, ſo foul a thing is it <hi>to hear the voice of conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy and not to utter it:</hi> and yet 'tis hard in our days to avoid the hearing of it almoſt in all places.</p>
            <p n="7">7. By <hi>unſeaſonable ſilence,</hi> and neglect of the Chriſtian duty of reprehenſion. <hi>Qui non vetat peccare, cum poteſt, jubet,</hi> He who is <hi>unactive</hi> for the King does <hi>paſſively rebel againſt him;</hi> and he <hi>bids</hi> who does not <hi>forbid</hi> ſuch outrages and violences to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt the <hi>Father of his Country.</hi> The miſchief intended by a <hi>Souldier</hi> againſt <hi>Craeſus,</hi> gave his <hi>Son a tongue,</hi> who never ſpoke before, to cry <hi>anthrope me kteine Creſon,</hi> man kill not <hi>Craeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now according to the <hi>degrees of your will and choice,</hi> and the <hi>tendency of your affections</hi> to this <hi>diſaſterous event,</hi> will <hi>your own Conſciences</hi> be beſt able to meaſure out your fearful expectations; which I the rather <hi>council you</hi> to do, becauſe men may <hi>dye an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal death,</hi> for that, upon which, our <hi>moſt indulgent Soveraign</hi> hath not thought fit, to <hi>inflict a temporal.</hi> Men may be <hi>damn'd</hi> for thoſe <hi>very ſins,</hi> which are <hi>pardon'd by an Act of Oblivion;</hi> the authority of the <hi>King of Heaven,</hi> being above any <hi>Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:101317:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Some thouſands, I believe, there were, both in your Kingdom and Ours, in the <hi>diminution of whoſe guilt,</hi> we may truly ſay, that <hi>through ignorance they did it,</hi> and that their crime lay more in <hi>their heads</hi> than in their <hi>hearts,</hi> and what they did, was, rather by the <hi>inſtigation</hi> of others, then any <hi>inclination</hi> of their own; being <hi>drawn into it</hi> by thoſe <hi>jugling Impoſtors,</hi> who upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of other mens livings, ſealed and delivered up their <hi>own conſciences</hi> to the Rebels ſervice, and pay'd them with the <hi>intereſt of as many more</hi> as they could ſeduce.</p>
            <p>Examine your conſciences therefore, whether you did not perceive ſome <hi>reluctancy</hi> then, for thoſe <hi>grand impieties,</hi> into which you were inveagled, <hi>ſome remorſe</hi> for them ſince? And do you not by ſo much the more <hi>abominate</hi> and <hi>deteſt the ſeducers,</hi> by how much the more they had <hi>deluded</hi> both your reaſon and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? Dare you not <hi>remember your Rebellious engagements</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſpleaſure! If not, though you at firſt <hi>entred</hi> into a <hi>complyance,</hi> even at the <hi>gate of Zeal,</hi> yet you have ſome reaſon to hope, that <hi>God will not lay this ſin to your charge;</hi> But hearken to <hi>the King's own prayer</hi> for you, which was, <q rend="inline">That God would bury this and all other their ſins in his Grave, that they might never riſe up again to work their <hi>deſperation</hi> in this World, or their <hi>damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in the next—That when God makes inquiſition for blood, he would ſprinkle your polluted yet penitent Souls with the blood of his Son, that his deſtroying Angel might paſs you over: for ſays the <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> As I doubt not but my blood will cry for vengeance to Heaven, ſo I beſeech God, not to pour out his wrath upon the <hi>generality of the People,</hi> who have either <hi>deſerted me</hi> or ingaged againſt me, through the <hi>artifice and hypocriſie of their Leaders.</hi>—That my temporal death unjuſtly inflicted by them, may not be revenged by God's juſt inflicting of Eternal death upon them; for I look upon the <hi>temporal deſtruction</hi> of the <hi>greateſt King,</hi> as far leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable than the <hi>Eternal damnation</hi> of the meaneſt Subject.—Though my deſtroyers forget their duty to thee or me, yet do not thou, O Lord, forget to be merciful to them, though they deſerve, yet let them not receive to themſelves damnation, but let <hi>the voyce of thy Son's blood</hi> be heard for my murderers <hi>louder</hi> than <hi>the cry of mine</hi> againſt them.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:101317:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Repentance</hi> is above <hi>half way to innocence,</hi> it changes <hi>the perſon</hi> with whom God is angry: Let us not therefore flatter our ſelves in any <hi>impenitent ſecurity,</hi> but <hi>bewail</hi> our ingagements in that <hi>fatall quarrel,</hi> and that <hi>the ſooner</hi> and <hi>the more,</hi> by how much the <hi>longer</hi> we have continued in it without any ſence or feeling: Let us <hi>lay the Sin to our conſciences</hi> for our amendment, that God may not <hi>lay it to our charges</hi> for condemnation, <hi>nor the King's blood be upon us, and our Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let us <hi>repay with intereſt</hi> that Obedience to <hi>the Son,</hi> which was <hi>due and in arrear</hi> to the <hi>Father;</hi> Submitting our ſelves as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi>Good Chriſtians and Subjects,</hi> to our now <hi>gracious Soveraign Lord King Charles the Second:</hi> Who is <hi>Heir apparent</hi> to that <hi>Love and Loyalty,</hi> which His <hi>Royal Father</hi> payed ſo dear for, as to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail it</hi> upon him this day, by a <hi>deed of Martyrdom.</hi> Let us pray to God, that he may be <hi>Trajano melior, &amp; Auguſto faelicior,</hi> more <hi>vertuous</hi> then <hi>Trajan,</hi> and more <hi>fortunate</hi> then <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and that the moſt righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth, may not make <hi>us drink ſo deep again</hi> of ſuch a <hi>cup of trembling,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>nor leave us to our ſelves and our Sins, nor impute His blood any farther to us; than to convince us, what need we have of Christ's blood, to waſh our Souls from the guilt of ſhedding His.</hi>
               </q> O Lord, we beſeech thee let not <hi>his Blood</hi> out-cry <hi>his Prayers,</hi> but let thoſe that <hi>ſpilt the one,</hi> obtain the <hi>benefit</hi> of the other; That by their <hi>Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Repentance, his Innocence</hi> may receive the happieſt atteſt; <hi>Our Religion</hi> be Vindicated from the Scandal of ſo horrid a fact; <hi>Our Nation</hi> be ſecured from the <hi>vengeance</hi> of that Blood, and the ſhedding more <hi>of the ſame Kind;</hi> and thy <hi>mercy glorified</hi> in the <hi>Converſion</hi> of ſo great Sinners, and all for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, to whom, with thee O Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, be all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Power and Glory, now, and for ever.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
